Inventory of the Sergeĭ Nikolaevich Paleolog Papers, 1920-1948
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergeĭ Nikolaevich Paleolog Papers,
1920-1948
34005
Paleolog, Sergeĭ Nikolaevich
42 manuscript boxes (16.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, and memoranda, relating to Russian refugees in Yugoslavia after the Russian Revolution and Civil War and the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary for the Settlement of Russian Refugees in Yugoslavia
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1934.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Chairman, Board of the Government Plenipotentiary for the Settlement of Russian Refugees in Yugoslavia.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, reports, and memoranda, relating to Russian refugees in Yugoslavia after the Russian Revolution and Civil War and the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary for the Settlement of Russian Refugees in Yugoslavia
Access Points
International relief.; Refugees.; Russians--Yugoslavia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Yugoslavia.
Container List
- File 1. General correspondence on the organization of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary for the settlement of Russian refugees in Yugoslavia, 1920-1921.
  Includes regulations, statements, and minutes
  - Parts 1-2, February 1920 - September 1921 (Folder 1: 1-15)
- File 2. Personnel applications, certificates, correspondence, lists, and form samples, 1920-1923
  - Part 1, January-July, 1920 (Folder 1: 16-21)
  - Part 2-3, August 1920 - December 1921 (Folder 2: 1-7)
  - Part 4, List of payments, 1920-1921 (Folder 2: 8-11)
  - Part 5, Curtailment of personnel and the winding up of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary, 1921-1922 (Folder 2: 12-14)
  - Part 6, Duties performed by S. N. Paleolog, 1920 (Folder 2: 15-16)
  - Part 7, Appraisement of S. N. Paleolog's work, and of refugee organizations and separate individuals, 1920-1923 (Folder 2: 17-20)
  - Part 8, Reorganization of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary and criticism of it by the radical émigré press, 1920-1921 (Folder 3: 1-6)
- File 3. Military assistant to the Government Plenipotentiary, finance representative and representative of state control, 1920-1921 (Folder 3, Folder 7-9)
- File 4. Committee for the Aid to Russian Refugees, correspondence, Parts 1-2, 1920-1921 (Folder 3: 10-17)
- File 5. Congress of the representatives of the refugee organizations, July 1920, Bureau of the Congresses, and refugee council 1920-1922 (Folder 3: 18-20)
- File 6. Russian Ambassador in Belgrade, Parts 1-2, 1920-1923 (Folder 4: 1-11)
- File 7. Russian Military Attaché in Yugoslavia, 1920-1921
  - Part 1, 1920 (Folder 4: 12-21)
  - Part 2, 1921-1922 (Folder 5: 1-5)
- File 8. Russian Red Cross Society in Yugoslavia, Parts 1-2, 1920-1922 (Folder 5: 6-19)
- File 9. All-Russian Zemstvo Union in Yugoslavia, 1920-1921 (Folder 6: 1-4)
- File 10. Joint Committee of the Russian Red Cross Society, All-Russian Zemstvo Union, the All-Russian Union of Township, and All-Russian Union of Township in Yugoslavia, 1921-1922 (Folder 6: 5-8)
- File 11. South-Russian Government, 1920-1922
  - Parts 1-2, 1920-1921 (Folder 6: 9-16, Folder 7: 1)
  - Part 3, Russian Council, 1921-1922 (Folder 7: 2)
- File 12. Statutes and Rules, Parts 1-2, 1918-1920 (Folder 7: 3-10)
- File 13. Orders and Enactments, 1920-1921 (Folder 7: 11-12)
  - Part 1, Orders, 1920-1921 (Folder 7: 11-12)
  - Part 2, Enactments, 1920 (Folder 7: 13)
- File 14. Regulations, 1920-1921
  - Part 1, 1920 (Folder 7: 14-16)
  - Part 2, 1921 (Folder 8: 1-3)
- File 15. Book of Reference--lists of colonies and other institutions, 1920 (Folder 8: 1-3)
- File 16. Department of Labor of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary, 1920-1921
  - Part 1, File of candidates, 1920-1921 (Folder 8: 7-11)
  - Part 2. Finding of work for refugees, 1920 (Folder 8: 12-14)
  - Part 3. Finding of work for refugees, 1921 (Folder 9: 1-7)
- File 17. Refugee's enterprises, 1920-1922
  - Part 1. Settlement on land and cooperatives, 1920 (Folder 9: 8-10)
  - Part 2. Dormitories, feeding centers, etc., 1920-1922 (Folder 9: 11-14)
- File 18. Correspondence concerning Russian invalids, 1920-1922 (Folder 9: 15-16, Folder 10: 1-3)
- Distribution of clothing and food to the refugees, 1920-1922 (Folder 10: 4-7)
- File 20. Donation for poor refugees and refugees evacuated from the Crimea, 1920-1922 (Folder 10: 8-9)
- File 21. The White Cross, the League of Nations, and the American Red Cross--help to the starving people in Russia, 1920-1922 (Folder 10: 10-13)
- File 22. The search for refugees and lost baggage, 1920-1921 (Folder 10: 14-18, Folder 11: 1-2)
- File 23. Individual payments from refugees, 1920-1922 (Folder 11: 3-7)
- File 24. Correspondence, 1920-1923
  - Part 1, Office correspondence of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary, 1921 (Folder 11: 8-15)
  - Parts 2-4, Letters addressed to S. N. Paleolog, 1920-1923 (Folder 12: 1-14)
  - Part 5, The press, 1920-1923 (Folder 12: 15-16)
- File 25. Department of Education of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary, 1920-1924
  - Part 1, Advisor for educational affairs in the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary and the Russian-Serbian Gymnasium in Belgrade, 1920-1922 (Folder 13: 1-4)
  - Part 2, Proceedings of the Academic Council attached to the Government commission, 1923-1924 (Folder 13: 5-7)
  - Part 3, Cadet schools in Yugoslavia, 1920-1922 (Folder 13: 8-15)
  - Part 4, Girls' schools in Yugoslavia, 1920-1922 (Folder 14: 1-5)
  - Part 5, Orphanages, 1920-1923 (Folder 14: 6-7)
- File 26. The Army, 1920-1925
  - Part 1, The Russian Army and the Commander in Chief, 1920-1925 (Folder 14: 8-11)
  - Part 2, Russian Officers' Association in Yugoslavia, 1920-1924 (Folder 14: 12-13)
  - Part 3, "Rusagen,", 1920-1922 (Folder 14: 14-16)
- File 27. Russian associations and unions in Yugoslavia, 1920-1921 (Folder 15: 1-8)
- File 28. Relations with the Serbian government, 1920-1925
  - Parts 1-2, 1920-1921 (Folder 15: 9-20)
  - Part 3, Government committee, 1920-1921 (Folder 16: 1-2)
  - Part 4, Government commission on Russian refugees, 1920-1922 (Folder 16: 3-5)
  - Part 5, Regarding Plentev and Chelnokov, 1920-1925 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Part 6, Searches of Russians and misunderstandings with the Serbs, 1921-1922 (Folder 16: 7-8)
- File 29. Disciplinary Courts, Honor Courts, Courts of Referees, 1921-1922
  - Parts 1-3, 1920-1921 (Folder 16: 9-16)
  - Parts 4-8, 1920-1921 (Folder 17: 1-16)
  - Parts 9-13, 1920-1921 (Folder 18: 1-16)
- File 30. Secret correspondence, 1920-1923
  - Parts 1-3, 1920-1921 (Folder 19: 1-16)
  - Part 4, Presentation of Russian Orders of Merits to foreigners for assistance rendered to Russian refugees, 1921-1923 (Folder 20: 1-2)
- File 31. Proceedings, 1920-1922
  - Part 1, Proceedings of the conference for the affairs of Russian refugees, 1920 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Parts 2-5, Proceedings of the committee to render assistance to Russian refugees in Yugoslavia, nos. 1-99, inclusive, 1920-1922 (Folder 20: 4-15, Folder 21: 1-4)
- File 32. Reports, 1920-1923
  - Part 1, Reports by the Government Plenipotentiary on the conditions of settlement and life of the Russian refugees in Yugoslavia, 1920 (Folder 21: 5)
  - Part 2, Report on the settlement of Russian refugees in Yugoslavia and on the activity of the Board of the Government Plenipotentiary from the beginning of evacuation to February 20, 1922, with the attached reports by the representatives of the Government Plenipotentiary: A. A. Khvostov, S. V. Iur'ev, A. A. Dabovskii, and P. S. Lopukhin, 1920-1922 (Folder 21: 6-8)
  - Part 3, Report by the Government Plenipotentiary on the activity of the board from the beginning of evacuation to March, 1922, with materials attached, 1920-1922 (Folder 21: 9-11)
  - Part 4, Reports of the Government Plenipotentiary on the appeal to the League of Nations concerning the settlement of Russian refugees in Yugoslavia, on the existing situation, the care of Russian refugees, etc., 1920-1921 (Folder 21: 12-15)
  - Part 5, Reports of the boards of Russian colonies in Yugoslavia, 1921-1923 (Folder 21: 16, Folder 22: 1-5)
  - Part 6, Reports on the reception of Russian refugees evacuated from the Crimea to Boka Cattaro by the representative of the Government Plenipotentiary V. F. Romanov, 1920-1921 (Folder 22: 6-7)
  - Part 7, Report on the reception and settlement of Russian refugees in Bosnia and Dalmatia by the representative of the Government Plenipotentiary A. A. Leman, 1920-1921 (Folder 22: 8)
  - Part 8, Appendix to A. A. Leman's report, 1920-1921 (Folder 22: 9)
  - Part 9, Report by the representative of the Government Plenipotentiary in Croatia and Slavonia P. M. Boiarskii (in duplicate), 1920 (Folder 22: 10)
  - Part 10, Travelling notes by the French Major Buxensuse, 1920 (Folder 22: 11)
  - Part 11, Travelling notes by a journalist Gleb Alekseev, 1920 (Folder 22: 12)
- File 33. Reception and settlement of refugees coming from North Russia (Former Army of General Yudenich) and report by D. S. Tverskoi in charge of evacuation from the Black Sea Ports, 1920 (Folder 22: 13)
- File 34. The closing down of the office of the Government Plenipotentiary in Boka Cattaro, 1921 (Folder 22: 14)
- File 35. Concerning the handling by P. A. Korbe of money and valuables brought by the former Chief of the Investigation Department in Sebastopol P. Sychev, 1920 (Folder 23: 1-2)
- File 36. Business correspondence of the representative of the Government Plenipotentiary A. A. Leman, 1920-1921
  - Part 1, Business correspondence,general, Nié region, 1920 (Folder 23: 3-6)
  - Part 2, Business correspondence on the organization and settlement of the refugees, Nié region, 1920 (Folder 23: 7-11)
  - Part 3, Business correspondence, Nié region, 1920-1921 (Folder 23: 12-15)
  - Part 4, Business correspondence, representation of the Government Plenipotentiary in Dalmatia. Includes orders and announcements, 1920-1921 (Folder 23: 16)
  - Business correspondence with the representative in Dalmatia, 1920-1921 (Folder 23: 17-18, Folder 24: 1-2)
  - Part 6, Account in Yadrinsk-Podunaev bank, 1920-1921 (Folder 24: 3)
- File 37. Business correspondence of the representative of the Government Plenipotentiary, P. M. Boiarskii, 1920-1921
  - Part 1, Business correspondence with the representative of P. M. Boiarskii in Croatia and Slovenia, 1920 (Folder 24: 4-19, Folder 25: 1-2, Folder 41: 16-17, Folder 42: 1-11)
  - Part 2, Business correspondence of the representative of P. M. Boiarskii in Dalmatia, 1920-1921 (Folder 25: 3-15, Folder 26: 1-9)
- File 38. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1924
  - Parts 1-2, January-March (Folder 26: 10-18)
  - Parts 3-6, April-December (Folder 27: 1-17, Folder 28: 1-2)
- File 39. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1925
  - Parts 1-3, January-May (Folder 28: 3-17, Folder 42: 12-19)
  - Parts 3-5, May-December (Folder 29: 1-16)
- File 40. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1926
  - Parts 1-3, January-July (Folder 29: 17, Folder 30: 1-17)
  - Part 4, July-December (Folder 31: 1-6)
- File 41. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1927
  - Parts 1-2, January-July (Folder 31: 7-17)
  - Parts 3-4, July-December (Folder 32: 1-9)
- File 42. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1928
  - Parts 1-2, January-August (Folder 32: 10-16)
  - Parts 2-3, August-December (Folder 33: 1-9)
- File 43. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1929
  - Part 1, January-May (Folder 33: 10-14)
  - Parts 2-3, May-December (Folder 34: 1-11)
- File 44. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1930
  - Parts 1-2, January-June (Folder 34: 12-16)
  - Parts 3-4, June-December (Folder 35: 1-10)
  - Part 5, Regulation no. 700, May 20, 1930 (Folder 35: 11-12)
- File 45. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1931
  - Part 1, January-April (Folder 35: 13-15)
  - Parts 2-3, May-December (Folder 36: 1-7)
- File 46. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1932
  - Parts 1-2, January-September (Folder 36: 8-16)
  - Part 3, September-December (Folder 37: 1-3)
- File 47. Miscellaneous correspondence, January 1 to April 1933 (Folder 37: 4-6)
- File 48. Public chest dedicated to the memory of Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich "Special Fund for the Salvation of Motherland"
  - Parts 1-6, correspondence concerning collection of donations to the "Fund for the Salvation of Motherland,", 1923-1929 (Folder 37: 7-16, Folder 38: 1-15, Folder 39: 1-5)
  - Part 7, correspondence regarding "Fund for the Salvation of Motherland" with the representative in the Far East J. A. Gleboff (I. A. Glebov), 1926-1929 (Folder 39: 6-10)
- File 49. Russian public chest for liberation (of Russia) dedicated to the memory of the Tsar-the Martyr, Nicholas II, Russkaia Osvoboditel'naia Kazna v Pamiat' Tsaria-Muchenika Nikolaia II-go, ("R.O.K."), 1927-1933
  - Part 1, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in Yugoslavia, 1930-1932 (Folder 39: 11-16)
  - Part 2, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in Bulgaria, Greece, Turkey, and Rumania, 1930-1932 (Folder 40: 1-4)
  - Part 3, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in Poland, Czechoslovakia, Finland, and Estonia, 1930-1932 (Folder 40: 5-12)
  - Part 4, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in Western Europe, 1930-1933 (Folder 40: 13-16)
  - Part 5, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in Egypt, Morocco, Palestine, Syria, and Tunis, 1930-1933 (Folder 40: 17-18, Folder 41: 1-2)
  - Part 6, Correspondence on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." in North and South America, Japan, Sumatra and Java, 1930-1932 (Folder 41: 3-11)
  - Part 7, Reports on the collection of contributions to the "R.O.K." from May 1, 1930 to May 1, 1932 with some literature re Bratstvo Russkoi Pravdy, 1927-1932 (Folder 41: 12)
- File 50. Government Plenipotentiary for the settlement of Russian refugees in Yugoslavia, G. E. Bozhinskii-Bozhko--liquidation of the office of the Government Plenipotentiary, 1921; 1933-1935,; 1948 (Folder 41: 13-15)
- See File 37. Part 1 (Folder 41: 16-17, Folder 42: 1-11)
- See File 39. Parts 1-3 (Folder 42: 12-19)